<page>
	<blog-basic>
		<date>02/02/2024</date>
		<title>Pale Fire</title>
		<subtitle>It's a book I read</subtitle>
		<keywords>nabokov, books, book review</keywords>
		<content>
			If you haven't read *Pale Fire* by Vladimir Nabokov, I'll just give you a summary: the book is a 999-line poem by John Shade, plus commentary by Dr. John Kinbote. I don't read much poetry, but I enjoyed it. It's a melancholy autobiography that I found beautiful at times. Well, "autobiography". Shade and Kinbote are characters made by Nabokov, and he uses this poem-plus-commentary framing to deliver a fascinating story of art, delusion, and bitter irony that made me say "Fuck you!" out loud once or twice. I recommend it, but I'd forgive you if you get bored reading the longer notes. I paused reading for several months after one of Kinbote's rambles, but I didn't regret coming back to finish the book.

			Over 200 lines of the poem are about Shade's daughter, Hazel, starting at line 290 through the end of Canto Two, kicking off Canto Three's themes of death and the afterlife. It's a moving section, painting a vivid picture of Hazel: a witty and creative introvert, suffering some unnamed chronic illness, grappling with loneliness and pain, dabbling in ghosts and the occult. It also paints a picture of John Shade, and the way his love for his daughter has fused with the sadness and pity he and his wife had for her. He sees her both as a clever, creative woman and a poor, sickly child.

			And most of all, it paints a picture of Kinbote, when he frames the whole section as a waste of space: "*[...] the reader cannot help feeling that it has been expanded and elaborated to the detriment of certain other richer and rarer matters ousted by it. But a commentator's obligations cannot be shirked, however dull the information he must collect and convey.*"
			Even though Kinbote's in control of the narrative, he can't help but come across as a bastard in the same way *Lolita*'s Humbert couldn't. His attempts to downplay the humanity of others only makes me sympathize with them more intensely.
		</content>
	</blog-basic>
</page>