<page>
	<title>Games with Haunted House Endings</title>
	<subtitle>Spoilers for various games!</subtitle>
	<keywords>videogames, game design, horror games</keywords>
	<date>08/19/2022</date>
	<content>
		<p>There's a subgenre of horror games I'd call "haunted houses". My platonic example would be <cite>Layers of Fear</cite>, a game where you explore the manor of a mad artist. The house shifts and changes as you go through, filled with frights and telling a story as you navigate each room.</p>
		<p>If you've played the game, hopefully this explains what I mean by a video game being a "haunted house". I'm talking about games that are light on mechanics, where you go through a linear or mostly-linear space meant to deliver thrills and a story as you go through, exactly like a real haunted house, using many of the same tricks. Rooms change their layout when you look away, actors do their performance as you go past. Surreal and disorienting visuals subtly guide you to the end of the experience.  You're meant to feel lost and confused, but somehow you get to the end without much trouble. There's no combat or meaningful "failure", though there are some simple puzzles to keep you involved and active.</p>
		<p>Most horror games have these elements, but it's a matter of emphasis. Games like Dead Space or Silent Hill certainly have spaces you explore, deliberately designed to scare and tell stories, but most of the scares come from enemies you have to deal with, and much of the story is told through dialog and cinematic events.</p>
		<p>In these haunted houses, the house is the main character. The house is the main antagonist. They also tend to be less intense and more contemplative than typical horror games. Exploring and inspecting the space isn't just something you can do, it's basically the <em>only</em> thing you can do. You're asked to understand what the space is trying to tell you.</p>
		<p>This blog isn't about this particular subgenre of horror games, it's about non-horror games that <em>end</em> with haunted houses. The existing mechanics take a back-seat to exploring a bespoke new area, the tone suddenly gets darker and more contemplative, and the game stops to show you <em>the point of it all</em> through the interpretive dance of moving rooms and collages of memories.</p>
		<p>It may sound somewhat 
	</content>
</page>