<basic-page>
	<title>/coCT/ - The /co/ OC Tournament</title>
	<content>
		<div>
			<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/fanart/group_small.png' alt='My group drawing of the contestants.'/>
		</div>
		<p>/coCT/ is an Original Character Tournament hosted on the /co/ 4chan board.</p>
		<p>OCTs are fun, so I decided to try hosting one on /co/, which is what I browse when I'm mentally unwell.</p>
		<p>Eight contestants entered their characters, and made comics of their opponents. Each round, I would decide which comic would continue, until only one story was the canon series of events for the tournament.</p>
		<p>It was a lot of fun, though keeping it up and running required me to be glued to 4chan almost 24/7, which isn't good for someone's brain. I'd love to see them continue, but it's so easy to lose track of competitors and for threads to go under. There's probably a reason 4chan isn't a usual venue for long-running tournaments. Still, I had fun, and I hope the competitors did, too.</p>
		<p>This is an archive for the tournament, containing every image I can remember being posted. If you want anything more uploaded, uh I have no idea how to message me reliably without also getting even more spam on my phone and email. Probably <a href='https://mastodon.social/@needleful'>my Mastodon page?</a> I could check that. There'll also probably be a few more /coCT/ threads in the future. I'm still waiting on IceLolly's comic, after all.</p>

		<h2>Full archive</h2>
		<p>All the images: <a href='/img/4oct/coct-2023.zip'>coct-2023.zip</a></p>
		<p>/coCT/ video, by Tuskanon: <a href='https://files.catbox.moe/4a950z.mp4'>coct-2023.mp4</a></p>

		<details>
			<summary>The Contestants</summary>
			<div>
				<h1>Bagman</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/bagman.jpg' />
				<p class='caption'>A half-bag, half-man, all muscle rough-and-tumbler looking for a good, honest fight.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Bushmonster</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/bushmonster2.png' />
				<p class='caption'>The elusive and mysterious swamp thing, drawn to the tournament's bright lights.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Callie</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/callie.jpg' />
				<p class='caption'>A character pulled from a cancelled game by Flargy-Filler and repurposed by a fan for this tournament, she's a girl who just wants to fight monsters caught in the tournament after getting killed and sent to Hell.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Cheras</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/cheras.png' />
				<p class='caption'>An immortal Baradostian meat creature who's always hungry.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Chulzeg the Covetous</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/chulzeg_the_covetous.png' />
				<p class='caption'>A gnarled filthy imp who drives people to act on their impulsive thoughts. This reference image also doubles as the audition comic, an inspiring example of efficiency and ingenuity.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>IceLolly-Bubblegum</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/icelolly2.png' />
				<p class='caption'>A young heroine teaching children how to stay safe online, though she spends most of her time getting caught in the very traps she's trying to teach people to avoid.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Radzlaw the Wizard</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/radzlaw_magic.png' />
				<p class='caption'>A necromancer who turned himself into a skeleton, as was the fashion of the time, but is sick of it and hopes winning the tournament will grant him living flesh again.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<h1>Tusk</h1>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/entries/tusk.jpg' />
				<p class='caption'>A beetle-man mercenary raised in a lab and hardened by tragedy. While hard and bitter, he's perhaps not the ball of violence he seems.</p>
			</div>
		</details>
		<br />
		<details>
			<summary>Thread links</summary>
			<p>Here's archived links to every thread. Hopefully they don't disappear, but maybe the archives will be archived.</p>
			<ul>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139039665'>First</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139049426'>Second</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139071115'>Third</a> (Round 1 starts)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139158001'>Fourth</a> (Round 2 starts plus Tusk lore)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139269697'>Fifth</a> (Short)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139295784'>Sixth</a> (Very short)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139324569'>Seventh</a> (So short I forgot to get a link and had to find it on desuarchive)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139344394'>Eighth</a> (Round 2 entries start here)</li>
				<li>Ninth: lost to time (It was only the OP)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139418789'>Tenth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139437252'>Eleventh</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139489482'>Twelfth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139599361'>Thirteenth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139611531'>Fourteenth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139656455'>Fifteenth</a> (Round 3 begins)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139745951'>Sixteenth</a> (IceLollyanon returned from the ether, still working on their Round 2 comic)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139745951'>Seventeenth</a></li>

				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139789279'> Eighteenth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139875307'> Nineteenth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139919681'> Twentieth</a></li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/139939735'> Twenty-First</a> (this is when the winner was announced)</li>
				<li><a href='https://desuarchive.org/co/thread/140007090'> Twenty-Second</a> (the final thread, for now, with most of the images)</li>
			</ul>
		</details>
		<br />
		<details>
			<summary>The Final Bracket (Spoilers)</summary>
				<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/round3/finale.png' />
		</details>
		<img class='comic' src='/img/4oct/extras/smal_host.png' />
		<p>Thanks to everyone who participated, and thank you for stopping by!</p>
	</content>
</basic-page>